Guide to the Alan K. Manchester Papers, 1905-1975 UA.29.02.0245
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alan K. Manchester papers
1905-1975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Manchester, Alan Krebs, b. 1897
UA.29.02.0245
2 Linear Feet
Alan K. Manchester (1897-1983) served as a faculty member in the Department of History at Duke University (1929-1967). Administrative positions held at Duke include Assistant Dean of Trinity College (1934), Dean of Freshmen (1935-1949), Dean of Undergraduate Studies (1949-1956), and Dean of Trinity College (1956-1964). Manchester also worked as a cultural affairs officer at the United States Embassy in Rio de Janeiro (1951-1952) and as a specialist for the U. S. State Department's International Exchange Service Program (Summers of 1954-55). Papers include correspondence, clippings, photographs, slides, and diaries. Records prior to 1929 pertain to Manchester's childhood and consist of old report cards, school programs, and correspondence. Later records reflect Manchester's activities as a historian, Foreign Service officer, and administrator. Major subjects include Latin American and South American history and economic and political relations between Brazil and Great Britain. The majority of the material is in English. Some material is in Spanish and Portuguese.
2,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Alan K. Manchester Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1983-1984.
Biographical and Historical Note
Educator, historian, cultural affairs liaison and consultant, and administrator. Born in Camden, New Jersey on July 2, 1897. Married Mary Elizabeth Onderdonk on June 28, 1922. Received A. B. from Vanderbilt University (1920), M. A. from Columbia University (1922), and Ph. D. from Duke University (1930). Positions held prior to employment at Duke: Instructor of English, Oklahoma University (1920-1921), Director, Moore Institute, Campinas, Sao Paolo, Brazil (1925-1927). Joined Duke faculty as an instructor in the History department (1929-1935). Eventually became an assistant professor (1935-1942), associate professor (1942-1950), and full professor (1950-1967). Eventually held a Distinguished Service Professorship at Duke. Administrative positions held at Duke include Assistant Dean of Trinity College (1934), Dean of Freshmen (1935-1949), Dean of Undergraduate Studies (1949-1956), and Dean of Trinity College (1956-1964). Retired in 1967. Other activities outside Duke University included cultural affairs officer at the United States Embassy in Rio de Janeiro (1951-1952), specialist for the U. S. State Department's International Exchange Service Program (Summers of 1954-55) and consultant (1956-1958). Died July 31, 1983 in Durham, N.C.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of correspondence, clippings, photographs, slides, and diaries, bulk 1929-1970. Records prior to 1929 pertain to Manchester's childhood and consist of old report cards, school programs, and correspondence. Later records reflect Manchester's activities as a historian, Foreign Service officer, and administrator
Related Material
Dean Alan K. Manchester Records, 1850-1967, bulk 1949-1967.
University Archives, Duke University.
Brazil -- Commerce -- Great Britain; Brazil -- Relations -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Commerce -- Brazil; Brazil -- Commerce -- History; Brazil -- History -- Study and teaching; South America -- History -- Study and teaching; Great Britain -- Relations -- Brazil; Latin America -- History -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Trinity College of Arts and Sciences; Manchester, Alan Krebs, b. 1897; Manchester, Alan Krebs, b. 1897; United States. Embassy (Brazil); Duke University. Department of History
- Subject Files, 1905-1970, bulk ca. 1920-1970, 1 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  These records contain letters congratulating Manchester on his appointment as Dean of Undergraduate Studies, retirement correspondence, and letters of appreciation usually from former students or their family members. Article clippings often concern Manchester's visits to various Latin American countries as either a Cultural Affairs Officer (1951-1952) or as a State Department Specialist (1954 and 1955). Some of these clippings are in Spanish and Portuguese. Also included are photographs of Manchester at various stages of life, construction on Duke's West Campus, and South America. Other papers consist of some of Manchester's personal writings and documents (such as passports and report cards), administrative and professional records (such as student course evaluations, reviews, and the functions and origins of the Dean of Undergraduate Studies), and civic and cultural activities and engagements.
  - Article-"The Growth of the Brazilian Bureaucracy, 1808-1821." (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews, 1938-1969 (Box 1)
  - Brazil
    - Clippings, 1951-1952, [3 folders] (Box 1)
    - Cultural Affairs Officer, 1951-1952, [2 folders] (Box 1)
    - Standard Phonic Drill Club, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Brazil, 1951-1952, South America, 1954-1955, and Canada, 1956. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - ca. 1931-1944 (Box 1)
    - 1933-1970 (Box 1)
    - ca. 1940-1968 (Box 1)
    - Letters of congratulations on appointment as Dean of Undergraduate Studies, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae and Retirement Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Duke University
    - Alumni Affairs: Off-Campus Activities, 1938-1962 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1934-1954 (Box 1)
    - ROTC, 1953-1964 (Box 1)
    - Student [Course] Evaluations, ca. 1960 and undated (Box 1)
    - Student [Course] Evaluations: "European Expansion and Imperialism," ca. 1966 (Box 1)
  - Inter-American Cultural Council, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Kiwanis Club, 1934-1962 (Box 1)
  - Masters Thesis, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, ca. 1925, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous scrapbook contents, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - National and International Activities, 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Personal Documents (Box 1)
  - Personal Writings and Recommendations of Manchester, ca. 1920 (Box 1)
  - Photos
    - Duke-related (Box 1)
    - Early photos (Box 1)
    - South America (Box 1)
  - Publications, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Publications and Related Material, 1930-1970 (Box 1)
  - Research Notes and an article rough draft (Box 1)
  - Retirement, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Seminar: Brazilian History, University of South Carolina, October 1967 (Box 1)
  - South America, 1954 and 1955, [2 folders] (Box 1)
  - South America-Clippings, 1954-1955, [3 folders] (Box 1)
  - Speaking Engagements and Other Activities: Cultural, Civic and Educational Organizations, 1936-1960 (Box 1)
  - Speaking Engagements and Other Activities: Cultural, Civic and Educational Organizations-Clippings, 1933-1966 (Box 1)
  - Symposia and Conferences, 1936-1966 (Box 1)
  - United Nations Activities-Clippings, 1956-1966 (Box 1)
- Slides, 1951-1968, 1 Linear Feet
  Arranged according to container number, the slides are images of Portugal, Spain, Europe, Latin America, Canada, New England, and various parts of North Carolina. The Latin America slides may have been taken while Manchester served as a Cultural Affairs Officer in Brazil (1951-1952) or as a Specialist for the State Department's International Exchange Service program. The Canadian slides were most likely taken when Manchester visited many Canadian universities and colleges while attending a Commonwealth Studies Conference in the summer of 1956. In addition to the slides, there exist logs for most of the slides and diaries of many of the trips. The logs contain codes for specific images on the slides, and the diaries are informal records of expenditures, miles covered, and activities.
  - Portugal, 1964, 1968 (Box 2, Slide-box 1-2)
  - Portugal, 1964, 1968 (Box 2, Slide-box 3)
  - Spain, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Europe: Copenhagen -- Lake Como, 1964 (Box 2, Slide-box 4)
  - Blue Ridge Parkway: Mabry Mill-- Grandfather Mtn., undated (Box 2, Slide-box 5)
  - Blue Ridge Parkway, Roan Mountain, Cherokee, Old Salem, Laurel Lake, Edenton, New Bern, Wilmington, Outer Banks, Gross Cottage, Atlantis (Box 2, Slide-box 6)
  - Duke Gardens, Duke Campus, Manchester residence (Box 2, Slide-box 7)
  - State Dept. Latin American Slide Collection: Durham--Medellin (Box 2, Slide-box 8)
  - State Dept. Latin American Slide Collection: Bogota--Piura (Box 2, Slide-box 9)
  - State Dept. Latin American Slide Collection: Peruvian Andes--Ouro Preto (Box 2, Slide-box 10)
  - State Dept. Latin American Slide Collection: Ouro Preto--Rio (Box 2, Slide-box 11)
  - State Dept. Latin American Slide Collection: Rio, Brasilia, Victoria (Box 2, Slide-box 12)
  - State Dept. Latin American Slide Collection: Salvador--Puerto Rico (Box 2, Slide-box 13)
  - State Dept. Latin American Slide Collection: Ontario--Victoria (Box 2, Slide-box 14)
  - Canadian Collection: Yellowstone, Mt. Rushmore, Badlands, Clayton, Cape Breton (Box 2, Slide-box 15)
  - Canadian Collection: Cape Breton, New England, La Gaspesie (Box 2, Slide-box 16)